Let’s now look at an order of operations
example. I will uncomment line 18,
making it live code. We have x plus 2 times y
and, in analyzing this code, one could come up
with two possible answers. X (five) plus 2 is
7 times 3 (for Y) is 21. That’s one possible
answer. Two times y is 6 plus 5 equals 11. That’s
the other possible answer. In a previous topic,
we covered order of operations with arithmetic,
so what do you think will be the answer: 21,
or 11? Let’s run the code and find out. The
answer is 11, because multiplication occurs
before addition in order of operations. Thus,
2 times y happens first, and then the result,
six, is added to x, five, to get 11. What if
we put parentheses around x plus 2? Will that
make a difference? Let’s find out. Indeed
it does, and now the result is 21 because,
whatever is inside parentheses in a calculation
is calculated first. X plus 2 is 7, and multiplied
by 3 y equals 21. Finally, let’s look at a unary
operator, which makes a positive value negative,
and a negative value positive. I will add a line
of code on line 20 to print the negative of x,
since x is a positive number. Adding +x will do
nothing here because x is already positive. But
printing -x prints negative 5. As is the case with
comparison and logical operators, understanding
the order of operations is critical to applying
the correct logic within code. Furthermore, the
more operators you know about with Python and any
other programming language, the less time you are
spending writing unnecessary code to work around
an operator you may not have known that exists.